A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Affairs, Office Files of Joseph E. Slater FA619
Rockefeller Archive Center
- GEOGRAPHIC FILES, 1957-1967; II
  - EUROPE/ATLANTIC, 2
    - Organizations
      For Atlantic Institute, see: Organization Files (Series IV). For Graduate Institute of International Studies, Geneva, see: Europe/Atlantic, European Free Trade Area. For PEP (Political and Economic Planning, London), see: Trip Notes (Series VI), Europe 1958-1959.
      - Atlantic Foundation - Memoranda, notes, 1962 March - 1959 June (Box 17, Folder 179)
      - Atlantic Foundation - Proposals, 1962 June - March 1960 (Box 17, Folder 180)
      - European Productivity Agency, 1959 June (Box 17, Folder 181)
        See also: Europe/Atlantic, economic development and integration.
    - Topics
      For 'East/West', see: Europe/Atlantic, Zbignew Brzezinski; Subject Files (Series V), Culture, Office of International Affairs; and Trip Notes (Series VI), USSR, 1964 August-October.
      - Atlantic partnership, 1963 November - 1961 September (Box 18, Folder 182)
      - Developing Countries - Comments re: Slater's July 1959 memorandum, 1959 August (Box 18, Folder 183)
      - Developing Countries - Latin America, 1964 January (Box 18, Folder 184)
      - Developing Countries - Miscellaneous correspondence, memoranda, 1966 March - 1957 May (Box 18, Folder 185)
      - Economy - Economic development and integration, 1963 November - 1959 November (Box 18, Folder 186)
      - Economy - European Free Trade Area, 1966 July - 1965 November (Box 18, Folder 187)
      - Education - Business and management, 1960 January (Box 18, Folder 188)
        See also: Trip Notes (Series VI), Richard Castalano trip notes, Europe 1966.
      - Education - Free University of Berlin, 1965 October - 1964 March (Box 18, Folder 189)
      - Education - Miscellaneous, 1963 June - 1960 July (Box 18, Folder 190)
      - Young Leaders Project - Correspondence, 1967 March - 1965 May (Box 18, Folder 191)
        See also: Trip Notes (Series VI), Paris, 1965 January & June-July; and Organization Files (Series IV), The Atlantic Institute.
      - Young Leaders Project - Drafts, memoranda, 1967 January - 1966 February (Box 18, Folder 192)
      - Young Leaders Project - Drafts, memoranda, notes, 1964 December - [n.d.] (Box 18, Folder 193)
      - Young Leaders Project - Lists of names and comments, 1966 January (Box 18, Folder 194-195)
      - Young Leaders Project - Memoranda, 1966 January - 1965 March (Box 18, Folder 196)
  - LATIN AMERICA, 3
    See also: Chronological Files (Series I) for equivalent dates.
    - Individuals
      For Alberto Lleras, see: Meeting Files (Series III), Encuentros', April 1965.
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1965 March - 1962 January (Box 19, Folder 197-198)
      - Miscellaneous correspondence, notes, [n.d.] = 1957 September (Box 19, Folder 199)
    - Organizations
      - ADELA (Atlantic Community Development Group for Latin America) - Annual reports, shareholder bulletins, 1966 June - 1965 April (Box 19, Folder 200)
      - ADELA (Atlantic Community Development Group for Latin America) - Correspondence: Jacob Javits, 1967 October - 1962 December (Box 19, Folder 201)
      - ADELA (Atlantic Community Development Group for Latin America) - Correspondence, memoranda, notes, 1964 December - 1963 March (Box 19, Folder 202)
      - ADELA (Atlantic Community Development Group for Latin America) - General information, 1964 December - 1962 November (Box 19, Folder 203)
      - Center for Inter-American Relations - Correspondence, 1967 January - 1966 March (Box 19, Folder 204)
      - Center for Inter-American Relations - Van Slyck, Philip: draft proposal, 1965 August (Box 19, Folder 205)
      - Center for Inter-American Relations - Van Slyck, Philip: final proposal, 1965 November (Box 20, Folder 206)
      - Center for Inter-American Relations - Van Slyck proposal: commentary, 1966 March - 1965 September (Box 20, Folder 207)
    - Topics
      - Economic development and integration - Meetings, 1967 April - 1966 September (Box 20, Folder 208)
      - Economic development and integration - Memoranda, 1967 April - 1966 November, 1963 March (Box 20, Folder 209)
- MEETING FILES, 1958-1967; III
  MEETING FILES are aranged in alphabetical order by title of the meeting, sponsor of the meeting, the place of the meeting, and meeting dates.
  The material within each folder is aranged in reverse chronological order.
  SERIES III, MEETING FILES (1958-1967), consists of 3 linear feet of correspondence, memoranda, notes, agendas, minutes, and background and meeting papers. This series includes all meetings except those of the Council on Foreign Relations and the International Broadcast Institute which are included in Series IV, ORGANIZATION FILES. Series II is made up of many different types of meetings: conferences, committees, seminars, colloquiums, formal and informal study groups, and briefings. Some were sponsored by the Ford Foundation and held internally, others resulted from Foundation grants and were held under the auspices of the grantees, while others matched Foundation interests and were attended by Mr. Slater in his capacity of staff member of the International Affairs program.
  - Arden House Meeting (on Latin America), 16-18 October 1959., 1959 October - September (Box 21, Folder 210)
  - University Seminar on the Atlantic Community, Columbia University, 1962-1963., 1963 February - 1962 May (Box 21, Folder 211)
  - Atlantic Conference of Political Youth Leaders, The Atlantic Treaty Association, Paris, July 7-11, 1958., 1958 July - May (Box 21, Folder 212)
  - Atlantic Relationaships, Eastern Europe and the United Nations, National Policy Panel, UNA-USA, June-November 1967., 1967 November - May (Box 21, Folder 213)
  - Berlin Advisory Group, Ford Foundation, 1963., 1963 April (Box 21, Folder 214)
  - Britain in the 1970s, New York University, Center for International Studies, April 7, 1966., 1966 March (Box 21, Folder 215)
  - Canada-United States Relationship, Canadian-American Assembley, Mont Gabriel, Quebec, June 23-26, 1964., 1964 November - June (Box 21, Folder 216)
  - Changing East-West Relations and the Unity of the West, European-American Colloquium, The Washington Center of Foreign Policy Research, May 1-2, 1964., 1964 November - June (Box 21, Folder 217)
  - Committee on Educational Interchange Policy, Institute of International Education, [seven meetings from] February 1962 - April 1964., 1964 April - 1962 February (Box 21, Folder 218, Box 22, Folder 219-224)
  - Conference on World Tensions, University of Chicago & World Brotherhood Inc., May 11-13, 1960., 1960 August - May (Box 22, Folder 225)
  - Cultural Projects for Berlin, U.S. Department of State, March 8, 1962., 1962 March (Box 22, Folder 226)
  - Seminar on Deterrence and Arms Control, Institute for Defense Analyses, July 25-27, 1960., 1963 July (Box 22, Folder 227)
  - [Economic development, informal discussion on], Carnegie Endowment International Center, October 12, 1959., 1959 October (Box 22, Folder 228)
  - Encuentros Siglo XX, Cuernavaca, Mexico, April 22-26, 1965., 1965 May - February (Box 22, Folder 229-230)
  - Encuentros Siglo XX, Paracas, Peru, June 2-5, 1966., 1966 August - 1965 November (Box 22, Folder 231)
  - Encuentros Siglo XX [plans for a third meeting], 1967 September - 1966 September 1966 (Box 22, Folder 232)
  - [Europe and the Atlantic Relationships], Ford Foundation, April 30, 1964., 1964 April - March (Box 22, Folder 233)
  - [Europe and the less developed nations], Ford Foundation, [proposed series of conferences]., 1960 January - 1959 September (Box 22, Folder 234)
  - European-American Colloquium, Villa Serbelloni, Bellagio, Itally, October 14-18, 1965., 1965 October (Box 22, Folder 235)
  - European Conference, November 26-28, 1965., 1965 November (Box 22, Folder 236)
  - European-Latin American Conference, Ford Foundation, Villa Serbelloni, Bellagio, Italy, October 4-9, 1964., 1964 October - May (Box 22, Folder 237)
  - [Foreign Economic Policy], Ford Foundation ad hoc committee, November 1959 - July 1959., 1959 July - 1958 November (Box 22, Folder 238)
    Includes material on the United States Free World Program of Economic Cooperation for Growth and Freedom.
  - [Foreign Economic Policy Project], [Joseph Slater's study group], New York, 1958-1959., 1963 July - 1958 May (Box 23, Folder 239-242)
    Includes material on the Private Initiative for International Economic Cooperation for Growth and Freedom.
  - Foreign Views on the Major Issues of the Sixties, The World Affairs Council of Northern California, August 20-21, 1963., 1963 August - 1963 July (Box 23, Folder 243)
  - Franklin Publications vis-a-vis USIA and AID, March 7, 1962., 1962 March (Box 23, Folder 244)
  - The Future of Europe, Federal Trust for Education and Research, Ditchley Park, England, February 18-20, 1966., 1966 February (Box 23, Folder 245)
  - The Future of the Atlantic Alliance, The University of Chicago, October 21-23, 1963., 1963 November - October (Box 23, Folder 246-247)
  - IA [International Affairs] Science Consultation, Ford Foundation, New York, February 9, 1966., 1966 February (Box 23, Folder 248)
  - IBM International Agencies Seminar, Poughkeepsie, N.Y., February 2-3, 1967, 1967 October - 1966 November (Box 23, Folder 249)
  - Impact of Science and Technology on International Relations, Ford Foundation, New York, February 20, 1963., 1963 February (Box 23, Folder 250)
  - Integrating Multi-Source Aid, Society for International Development, April 4-6, 1963., 1963 March - February (Box 23, Folder 251)
  - Inter-American Exchange of Persons, International Institute of Education, Puerto Rico, October 14-18, 1958., 1959 March - 1958 October (Box 24, Folder 252-253)
    See also: Third National Conference on Exchange of Persons.
  - Inter-American Press Association, Annual Meeting, San Francisco, October 6-8, 1959., 1959 October - 1958 October (Box 24, Folder 254)
  - Internal and External Factors in Development in the South Asia-Pacific Region, Council on World Tensions [proposed conference], Kuala Lumpur., 1963 August - 1962 November (Box 24, Folder 255)
  - International Committee Meetings, National Planning Association, December 1961 - March 1965., 1965 December - 1961 November (Box 24, Folder 256-257)
  - International Conference on Defense and Strategy, Harvard University, Center for International Affairs, May 31-June 9, 1963., 1963 June - May (Box 24, Folder 258)
  - International Institute for Books, National Academy of Sciences, September 13, 1966., 1966 September (Box 24, Folder 259)
  - Intervention and the American Purpose: Cuba 1962, Airlie Conference, March 13-17, 1963., 1963 March (Box 24, Folder 260)
  - [Japan and the Free World Economy], Committee for Economic Development, Tokyo, Japan, October 16-23, 1962., 1962 October (Box 24, Folder 261)
  - Japanese-American Conference, Williamsburg, Virginia, April 4-9, 1967., 1967 April (Box 24, Folder 262)
  - Japanese-American Roundtable Conference on Current International Problems, Dartmouth College, October 1-7, 1962., 1962 November - September (Box 25, Folder 263)
  - [Japanese Science], Washington D.C., December 1, 1962., 1962 December - May (Box 25, Folder 264)
  - Manpower Planning and Development, Ford Foundation Study Committee, 1965., 1965 November - February (Box 25, Folder 265)
  - The Meaning of Commercial Television, University of Texas & Stanford University, Asilomar, CA, April 24-26, 1966., 1966 April - February (Box 25, Folder 266)
  - The National Security Policy of the United States, U.S. Military Academy, West Point, N.Y., December 2-5, 1959., 1960 February - October 1959 (Box 25, Folder 267)
  - Outer Space: Prospects for Man and Society, European American Assembly, Brighton, England, May 13-16, 1962., 1962 May (Box 25, Folder 268)
  - Patterns of Economic and Social Change, Preparatory Study Commission, National Council of Churches, Department of International Affairs, January - June 1963., 1963 June - January (Box 25, Folder 269)
  - Personnel for Overseas Development, Ford Foundation, New York, 1962., 1962 Decemer - March (Box 25, Folder 270)
  - Planning and Development of New Towns, United Nations Roundtable Conference, Moscow, USSR, August 24 - September 7, 1964., 1964 August (Box 25, Folder 271)
  - Planning for National Security, [Roger Hilsman's informal committee], Washington, D.C., 1959-1960., 1960 May - 1959 April (Box 25, Folder 272)
  - Private Enterprise's Social Responsibility, Creole Foundation, New York, March 12, 1964., 1964 March - June (Box 25, Folder 273)
  - [Projections in the Future], Herman Kahn, Hudson Institute, May 3, 1967., 1967 June - March (Box 25, Folder 274)
  - Racial Issues in American Foreign Policy, University of Denver, July 27-30, 1967., 1967 May - 1966 February (Box 25, Folder 275)
  - [Science Cooperation, Taiwan], NAS Committee Briefing, National Academy of Sciences, Washington D.C., June 22, 1964., 1964 June - April (Box 26, Folder 276)
  - The Security of Southern Asia, Institute for Strategic Studies, August 16-18, 1963., 1963 November - June (Box 26, Folder 277)
  - Tensions in Development in the Western Hemisphere, Council on World Tensions, Bahia, Brazil, August 6-11, 1962., 1962 September - July (Box 26, Folder 278)
  - Third National Confernce on Exchange of Persons, International Institute of Education, Washington D.C., January 28-31, 1959., 1959 February - 1958 November (Box 26, Folder 279-280)
  - United Nations Policy Studies Program, Brookings Institution, Washington D.C., 1963., 1963 November - June (Box 26, Folder 281)
  - The United States and Eastern Europe, The American Assembly, April 27-30, 1967., 1967 April (Box 26, Folder 282)
  - The United States and Japan, The American Assembly, October 28-31, 1965., 1965 October (Box 26, Folder 283)
  - [U.S.-French Roundtable], Ford Foundation, [proposed conference], December 1964-May 1966., 1966 May - 1964 December (Box 26, Folder 284)
    Includes correspondence to/from Michel Gordey.
- ORGANIZATION FILES, 1957-1967; IV
  ORGANIZATION FILES are arranged in alphabetical order. Organization files containing diverse material are aranged alphabetically by section. The material within each folder is arranged in reverse chronological order.
  For ADELA Investment Company, see: Geographic Files (Series II), Latin America, Organizations; and Asia/Pacific, Organizations. For Asian Broadcasting Union, see: Geographic Files (Series II), Asia/Pacific, Organizations. For Center for Inter-American Relations, see: Geographic Files (Series II), Latin America, Organizations. For Center for Southeast Asian Studies, see: Trip Notes (Series VI), Japan, 1966 July. For European Productivity Agency, see: Geographic Files (Series II), Europe/Atlantic, Organizations. For Graduate Institute of International Studies, Geneva, see: Geographic Files (Series II), Europe/Atlantic, European Free Trade Area. For Maison des Sciences de l'Homme (Center of Human Sciences, Paris) see: Trip Notes (Series VI), Paris, 1964 June. For Overseas Development Institute, see: Geographic Files (Series II), Europe/Atlantic, developing countries; Trip Notes (Series VI), Europe, 1958-1959. For PEP (Political and Economic Planning, London) see: Trip Notes (Series VI), Europe, 1958-1959.
  SERIES IV, ORGANIZATION FILES (1957-1967), consists of 3.75 linear feet of reports, correspondence, memoranda, and notes. These files also include the material generated by the following broad study groups of the Council on Foreign Relations: Atlantic Policy Studies, (Atlantic-related study and discussion groups), The United States and China in World Affairs, U.S. Aid Policies and Programs in Viet Nam, Science and Foreign Policy, and Science and the National Interest. Also included is some meeting material of the International Broadcast Institute.
  - The American Assembly, 1967 September - 1962 December (Box 27, Folder 285)
    See also: Meeting Files (Series III), The United States and Eastern Europe; The United States and Japan.
  - The Atlantic Institute - Correspondence, 1967 July - 1961 March (Box 27, Folder 286)
  - The Atlantic Institute - Meetings, minutes and summaries, 1966 April - 1965 June (Box 27, Folder 287)
  - The Atlantic Institute - Memoranda, 1967 June - 1959 October (Box 27, Folder 288)
  - The Atlantic Institute - NATO Parliamentarians Project, 1965 November - 1963 June (Box 27, Folder 289-290)
    Includes background material.
  - The Atlantic Institute - Progress Reports, 1963 February, 1960 September (Box 27, Folder 291)
  - The Atlantic Institute - Projects, proposals, guidelines, 1966 April - [1960?] (Box 27, Folder 292-293)
  - The Atlantic Institute - U.S.-EEC project, 1962 December - August (Box 27, Folder 294)
  - The Atlantic Institute - Young Leaders Project, 1967 April - 1965 May (Box 27, Folder 295)
    See also: Geographic Files (Series I), Europe/Atlantic, young leaders; Trip Notes (Series VI), Paris, 1965 January, & June-July.
  - Brookings Institution, 1962 August - 1961 May (Box 27, Folder 296)
    See also: Meeting Files (Series III), U.N. Policy Studies Program; Organization Files (Series IV), UNITAR, Cox correspondence.
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Atlantic Policy Studies - Atlantic Agriculture, 1964 December - October (Box 28, Folder 297)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Atlantic Policy Studies - The Atlantic Community and the Underdeveloped Countries, 1966 January (Box 28, Folder 298)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Atlantic Policy Studies - Atlantic Monetary Arrangements, 1965 December - 1964 November (Box 28, Folder 299)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Atlantic Policy Studies - Atlantic Trade and Economic Arrangements, 1965 December - 1963 December (Box 28, Folder 300-301)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Atlantic Policy Studies - External Environment of the Atlantic Community, 1963 December (Box 28, Folder 302)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Atlantic Policy Studies - Planning Group Meeting, 1962 December (Box 28, Folder 303)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Atlantic Policy Studies - Review Group on Geiger Manuscript, 1966 January - 1963 November (Box 28, Folder 304)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Atlantic Policy Studies - Steering Committee, 1965 October - 1963 December (Box 28, Folder 305-309)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Atlantic Policy Studies - Western Strategy and Military Organization, 1964 September - 1963 December (Box 28, Folder 310-311)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - [Atlantic-related study and discussion groups] - An Atlantic Assembly, 1963 January (Box 29, Folder 312)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - [Atlantic-related study and discussion groups] - Military Stability and Political Evolution in Europe, 1967 April - 1966 July (Box 29, Folder 313)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - [Atlantic-related study and discussion groups] - The OECD (Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development), 1964 April - February (Box 29, Folder 314)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - [Atlantic-related study and discussion groups] - Strategy and Foreign Policy, 1961 March - 1960 March (Box 29, Folder 315)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - The United States and China in World Affairs - American Public Attitudes Toward China, 1964 September - 1963 May (Box 30, Folder 316)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - The United States and China in World Affairs - China-Atlantic Steering Committees, Joint Meeting, 1967 January - 1966 December (Box 30, Folder 317)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - The United States and China in World Affairs - Negotiations and contacts between the United States and Communist China: Study Group, 1965 June (Box 30, Folder 318)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - The United States and China in World Affairs - Steering Committee, 1966 January - 1962 April (Box 30, Folder 319-328)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - The United States and China in World Affairs - U.S. Security and Alliance Policies in Asia, 1965 July - May (Box 30, Folder 329)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - U.S. Aid Policies and Programs in Viet Nam - Study Group, 1960 June - 1959 October (Box 31, Folder 330-333)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Science and Foreign Policy - Discussion Group, 1964 December - 1963 March (Box 31, Folder 334-335)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Science and the National Interest - Discussion Group, 1966 November - March (Box 31, Folder 336-339)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Correspondence - Blum, Robert, 1965 May - 1963 January (Box 32, Folder 340)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Correspondence - Memberships, 1967 June - 1962 April (Box 32, Folder 341)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Miscellaneous - Air Force Installation Tour, 1967 November - 1958 May (Box 32, Folder 344)
  - Council on Foreign Relations - Miscellaneous - Dinner/Luncheon Meetings, 1967 October - 1959 November (Box 32, Folder 345)
  - Hudson Institute, 1965 June - 1964 August (Box 33, Folder 346)
  - Institute for Strategic Studies, 1966 October - 1958 October (Box 33, Folder 347)
  - Institute of International Education, 1965 March - 1961 July (Box 33, Folder 348)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Charter, 1967 May - 1966 June (Box 34, Folder 349-350)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Correspondence - Cowan, Louis, 1966 December - 1965 November, 1962 December (Box 34, Folder 351-352)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Correspondence - Cowan with non-Foundation individuals, 1966 September - March (Box 34, Folder 353)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Correspondence - Mickelson, Sig, 1968 April - 1966 May (Box 34, Folder 354)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Correspondence - Miscellaneous, 1967 July - 1965 September (Box 34, Folder 355-358)
    Includes correspondence to/from William Benton, Michel Gordey, Maurice Mitchell, Aurelio Peccei, and George Probst.
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Correspondence - Miscellaneous re: members, 1967 October - 1965 December (Box 34, Folder 359-360)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Correspondence - Webster, David, 1967 September - 1965 September (Box 34, Folder 361)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Meetings - Bellagio - Correspondence, 1966 April - 1965 December (Box 35, Folder 362)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Meetings - Bellagio - notes and agendas, 1966 March - January (Box 35, Folder 363)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Meetings - Bellagio - Reports, 1966 March - February (Box 35, Folder 364)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Meetings - Post-Bellagio, 1967 June - March, 1966 April - March (Box 35, Folder 365)
  - International Broadcast Institute (IBI) - Reports, 1967 December - 1965 December (Box 35, Folder 366-369)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development (OECD), 1966 October - 1965 August, 1963 October - March (Box 36, Folder 370-371)
    See also: Council on Foreign Relations, OECD study.
  - United Nations - Correspondence: Finklestein, Lawrence, 1962 October - August (Box 36, Folder 372)
    See also: Meeting Files (Series III), United Nations Policy Studies Program; Subject Files (Series V), Office of International Affairs.
  - United Nations - Miscellaneous, 1967 September, 1965 April, 1962 March (Box 36, Folder 373)
  - United Nations - Proposal: Peacekeeping in the Congo, 1964 June - 1963 October (Box 36, Folder 374)
  - United Nations - Study: Finklestein, Lawrence, 1962 July - June (Box 36, Folder 375-376)
  - United Nations-affiliated organizations - International Labor Organization, 1964 September - 1963 September (Box 36, Folder 377)
  - United Nations-affiliated organizations - U.N. International School, 1967 May, 1964 January (Box 36, Folder 378)
  - United Nations-affiliated organizations - UNA-USA, 1967 September - 1965 November (Box 36, Folder 379)